<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-07-04T13:09:15+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Gorav Jindal&apos;s personal and academic webpage
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Hardness of Quantum Distribution Learning and Quantum Cryptography</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-hardness-of-quantum-distribution-learning-and-quantum-cryptography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Complexity: Hardness of Quantum Distribution Learning and Quantum Cryptography" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-hardness-of-quantum-distribution-learning-and-quantum-cryptography</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-hardness-of-quantum-distribution-learning-and-quantum-cryptography/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Taiga+Hiroka">Taiga Hiroka</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Min-Hsiu+Hsieh">Min-Hsiu Hsieh</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Tomoyuki+Morimae">Tomoyuki Morimae</a></p>

<p>The existence of one-way functions (OWFs) forms the minimal assumption in
classical cryptography. However, this is not necessarily the case in quantum
cryptography. One-way puzzles (OWPuzzs), introduced by Khurana and Tomer,
provide a natural quantum analogue of OWFs. The existence of OWPuzzs implies
$PP\neq BQP$, while the converse remains open. In classical cryptography, the
analogous problem-whether OWFs can be constructed from $P \neq NP$-has long
been studied from the viewpoint of hardness of learning. Hardness of learning
in various frameworks (including PAC learning) has been connected to OWFs or to
$P \neq NP$. In contrast, no such characterization previously existed for
OWPuzzs. In this paper, we establish the first complete characterization of
OWPuzzs based on the hardness of a well-studied learning model: distribution
learning. Specifically, we prove that OWPuzzs exist if and only if proper
quantum distribution learning is hard on average. A natural question that
follows is whether the worst-case hardness of proper quantum distribution
learning can be derived from $PP \neq BQP$. If so, and a worst-case to
average-case hardness reduction is achieved, it would imply OWPuzzs solely from
$PP \neq BQP$. However, we show that this would be extremely difficult: if
worst-case hardness is PP-hard (in a black-box reduction), then $SampBQP \neq
SampBPP$ follows from the infiniteness of the polynomial hierarchy. Despite
that, we show that $PP \neq BQP$ is equivalent to another standard notion of
hardness of learning: agnostic. We prove that $PP \neq BQP$ if and only if
agnostic quantum distribution learning with respect to KL divergence is hard.
As a byproduct, we show that hardness of agnostic quantum distribution learning
with respect to statistical distance against $PPT^{\Sigma_3^P}$ learners
implies $SampBQP \neq SampBPP$.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Taiga Hiroka, Min-Hsiu Hsieh, Tomoyuki Morimae]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Complexity: PCPP-Based Reconfiguration Inapproximability: Query Complexity vs. Soundness Gap Trade-offs</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-pcpp-based-reconfiguration-inapproximability-query-complexity-vs-soundness-gap-trade-offs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Complexity: PCPP-Based Reconfiguration Inapproximability: Query Complexity vs. Soundness Gap Trade-offs" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-pcpp-based-reconfiguration-inapproximability-query-complexity-vs-soundness-gap-trade-offs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-pcpp-based-reconfiguration-inapproximability-query-complexity-vs-soundness-gap-trade-offs/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Venkatesan+Guruswami">Venkatesan Guruswami</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Xuandi+Ren">Xuandi Ren</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Kewen+Wu">Kewen Wu</a></p>

<p>The Reconfiguration Inapproximability Hypothesis (RIH), recently established
by Hirahara-Ohsaka (STOC’24) and Karthik-Manurangsi (ECCC’24), studies the
hardness of reconfiguring one solution into another in constraint satisfaction
problems (CSP) when restricted to approximate intermediate solutions. In this
work, we make a tighter connection between RIH’s soundness gap and that of
probabilistically checkable proofs of proximity (PCPP). Consequently, we
achieve an improved trade-off between soundness and query complexity in Gap CSP
Reconfiguration. Our approach leverages a parallelization framework, which also
appears in some recent parameterized inapproximability results.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Venkatesan Guruswami, Xuandi Ren, Kewen Wu]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Complexity: Symport/Antiport P Systems with Membrane Separation Characterize P^(#P)</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-symport-antiport-p-systems-with-membrane-separation-characterize-p-p/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Complexity: Symport/Antiport P Systems with Membrane Separation Characterize P^(#P)" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-symport-antiport-p-systems-with-membrane-separation-characterize-p-p</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-complexity-symport-antiport-p-systems-with-membrane-separation-characterize-p-p/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Vivien+Ducros">Vivien Ducros</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Claudio+Zandron">Claudio Zandron</a></p>

<p>Membrane systems represent a computational model that operates in a
distributed and parallel manner, inspired by the behavior of biological cells.
These systems feature objects that transform within a nested membrane
structure. This research concentrates on a specific type of these systems,
based on cellular symport/antiport communication of chemicals.
Results in the literature show that systems of this type that also allow cell
division can solve PSPACE problems. In our study, we investigate systems that
use membrane separation instead of cell division, for which only limited
results are available. Notably, it has been shown that any problem solvable by
such systems in polynomial time falls within the complexity class P^(#P).
By implementing a system solving MIDSAT, a P^(#P)-complete problem, we
demonstrate that the reverse inclusion is true as well, thus providing an exact
characterization of the problem class solvable by P systems with
symport/antiport and membrane separation.
Moreover, our implementation uses rules of length at most three. With this
limit, systems were known to be able to solve NP-complete problems, whereas
limiting the rules by length two, they characterize P.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Vivien Ducros, Claudio Zandron]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Geometry: A Stable and Theoretically Grounded Gromov-Wasserstein Distance for Reeb Graph Comparison using Persistence Images</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-a-stable-and-theoretically-grounded-gromov-wasserstein-distance-for-reeb-graph-comparison-using-persistence-images/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Geometry: A Stable and Theoretically Grounded Gromov-Wasserstein Distance for Reeb Graph Comparison using Persistence Images" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-a-stable-and-theoretically-grounded-gromov-wasserstein-distance-for-reeb-graph-comparison-using-persistence-images</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-a-stable-and-theoretically-grounded-gromov-wasserstein-distance-for-reeb-graph-comparison-using-persistence-images/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Erin+W.+Chambers">Erin W. Chambers</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Guangyu+Meng">Guangyu Meng</a></p>

<p>Reeb graphs are a fundamental structure for analyzing the topological and
geometric properties of scalar fields. Comparing Reeb graphs is crucial for
advancing research in this domain, yet existing metrics are often
computationally prohibitive or fail to capture essential topological features
effectively. In this paper, we explore the application of the
Gromov-Wasserstein distance, a versatile metric for comparing metric measure
spaces, to Reeb graphs. We propose a framework integrating a symmetric variant
of the Reeb radius for robust geometric comparison, and a novel probabilistic
weighting scheme based on Persistence Images derived from extended persistence
diagrams to effectively incorporate topological significance. A key
contribution of this work is the rigorous theoretical proof of the stability of
our proposed Reeb Gromov-Wasserstein distance with respect to perturbations in
the underlying scalar fields. This ensures that small changes in the input data
lead to small changes in the computed distance between Reeb graphs, a critical
property for reliable analysis. We demonstrate the advantages of our approach,
including its enhanced ability to capture topological features and its proven
stability, through comparisons with other alternatives on several datasets,
showcasing its practical utility and theoretical soundness.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Erin W. Chambers, Guangyu Meng]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Multiple Watchman Routes in Staircase Polygons</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-multiple-watchman-routes-in-staircase-polygons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Geometry: Multiple Watchman Routes in Staircase Polygons" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-multiple-watchman-routes-in-staircase-polygons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-multiple-watchman-routes-in-staircase-polygons/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Anna+Br%C3%B6tzner">Anna Brötzner</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Bengt+J.+Nilsson">Bengt J. Nilsson</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Christiane+Schmidt">Christiane Schmidt</a></p>

<p>We consider the watchman route problem for multiple watchmen in staircase
polygons, which are rectilinear $x$- and $y$-monotone polygons. For two
watchmen, we propose an algorithm to find an optimal solution that takes
quadratic time, improving on the cubic time of a trivial solution. For $m \geq
3$ watchmen, we explain where this approach fails, and present an approximation
algorithm for the min-max criterion with only an additive error.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Anna Brötzner, Bengt J. Nilsson, Christiane Schmidt]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Computational Geometry: Search-Based Robot Motion Planning With Distance-Based Adaptive Motion Primitives</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-search-based-robot-motion-planning-with-distance-based-adaptive-motion-primitives/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Computational Geometry: Search-Based Robot Motion Planning With Distance-Based Adaptive Motion Primitives" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-search-based-robot-motion-planning-with-distance-based-adaptive-motion-primitives</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-computational-geometry-search-based-robot-motion-planning-with-distance-based-adaptive-motion-primitives/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Benjamin+Kraljusic">Benjamin Kraljusic</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Zlatan+Ajanovic">Zlatan Ajanovic</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Nermin+Covic">Nermin Covic</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Bakir+Lacevic">Bakir Lacevic</a></p>

<p>This work proposes a motion planning algorithm for robotic manipulators that
combines sampling-based and search-based planning methods. The core
contribution of the proposed approach is the usage of burs of free
configuration space (C-space) as adaptive motion primitives within the graph
search algorithm. Due to their feature to adaptively expand in free C-space,
burs enable more efficient exploration of the configuration space compared to
fixed-sized motion primitives, significantly reducing the time to find a valid
path and the number of required expansions. The algorithm is implemented within
the existing SMPL (Search-Based Motion Planning Library) library and evaluated
through a series of different scenarios involving manipulators with varying
number of degrees-of-freedom (DoF) and environment complexity. Results
demonstrate that the bur-based approach outperforms fixed-primitive planning in
complex scenarios, particularly for high DoF manipulators, while achieving
comparable performance in simpler scenarios.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Benjamin Kraljusic, Zlatan Ajanovic, Nermin Covic, Bakir Lacevic]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Deterministic Partition Tree and Applications</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-a-deterministic-partition-tree-and-applications/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: A Deterministic Partition Tree and Applications" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-a-deterministic-partition-tree-and-applications</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-a-deterministic-partition-tree-and-applications/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Haitao+Wang">Haitao Wang</a></p>

<p>In this paper, we present a deterministic variant of Chan’s randomized
partition tree [Discret. Comput. Geom., 2012]. This result leads to numerous
applications. In particular, for $d$-dimensional simplex range counting (for
any constant $d \ge 2$), we construct a data structure using $O(n)$ space and
$O(n^{1+\epsilon})$ preprocessing time, such that each query can be answered in
$o(n^{1-1/d})$ time (specifically, $O(n^{1-1/d} / \log^{\Omega(1)} n)$ time),
thereby breaking an $\Omega(n^{1-1/d})$ lower bound known for the semigroup
setting. Notably, our approach does not rely on any bit-packing techniques. We
also obtain deterministic improvements for several other classical problems,
including simplex range stabbing counting and reporting, segment intersection
detection, counting and reporting, ray-shooting among segments, and more.
Similar to Chan’s original randomized partition tree, we expect that additional
applications will emerge in the future, especially in situations where
deterministic results are preferred.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Haitao Wang]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Breaking the $n^{1.5}$ Additive Error Barrier for Private and Efficient Graph Sparsification via Private Expander Decomposition</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-breaking-the-n-1-5-additive-error-barrier-for-private-and-efficient-graph-sparsification-via-private-expander-decomposition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Breaking the $n^{1.5}$ Additive Error Barrier for Private and Efficient Graph Sparsification via Private Expander Decomposition" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-breaking-the-n-1-5-additive-error-barrier-for-private-and-efficient-graph-sparsification-via-private-expander-decomposition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-breaking-the-n-1-5-additive-error-barrier-for-private-and-efficient-graph-sparsification-via-private-expander-decomposition/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Anders+Aamand">Anders Aamand</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Justin+Y.+Chen">Justin Y. Chen</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Mina+Dalirrooyfard">Mina Dalirrooyfard</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Slobodan+Mitrovi%C4%87">Slobodan Mitrović</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Yuriy+Nevmyvaka">Yuriy Nevmyvaka</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Sandeep+Silwal">Sandeep Silwal</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Yinzhan+Xu">Yinzhan Xu</a></p>

<p>We study differentially private algorithms for graph cut sparsification, a
fundamental problem in algorithms, privacy, and machine learning. While
significant progress has been made, the best-known private and efficient cut
sparsifiers on $n$-node graphs approximate each cut within
$\widetilde{O}(n^{1.5})$ additive error and $1+\gamma$ multiplicative error for
any $\gamma &gt; 0$ [Gupta, Roth, Ullman TCC’12]. In contrast, “inefficient”
algorithms, i.e., those requiring exponential time, can achieve an
$\widetilde{O}(n)$ additive error and $1+\gamma$ multiplicative error
[Eli{'a}{\v{s}}, Kapralov, Kulkarni, Lee SODA’20]. In this work, we break the
$n^{1.5}$ additive error barrier for private and efficient cut sparsification.
We present an $(\varepsilon,\delta)$-DP polynomial time algorithm that, given a
non-negative weighted graph, outputs a private synthetic graph approximating
all cuts with multiplicative error $1+\gamma$ and additive error $n^{1.25 +
o(1)}$ (ignoring dependencies on $\varepsilon, \delta, \gamma$).
At the heart of our approach lies a private algorithm for expander
decomposition, a popular and powerful technique in (non-private) graph
algorithms.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Anders Aamand, Justin Y. Chen, Mina Dalirrooyfard, Slobodan Mitrović, Yuriy Nevmyvaka, Sandeep Silwal, Yinzhan Xu]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Dynamic Similarity Graph Construction with Kernel Density Estimation</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-dynamic-similarity-graph-construction-with-kernel-density-estimation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Dynamic Similarity Graph Construction with Kernel Density Estimation" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-dynamic-similarity-graph-construction-with-kernel-density-estimation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-dynamic-similarity-graph-construction-with-kernel-density-estimation/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Steinar+Laenen">Steinar Laenen</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Peter+Macgregor">Peter Macgregor</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=He+Sun">He Sun</a></p>

<p>In the kernel density estimation (KDE) problem, we are given a set $X$ of
data points in $\mathbb{R}^d$, a kernel function $k: \mathbb{R}^d \times
\mathbb{R}^d \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$, and a query point $\mathbf{q} \in
\mathbb{R}^d$, and the objective is to quickly output an estimate of
$\sum_{\mathbf{x} \in X} k(\mathbf{q}, \mathbf{x})$. In this paper, we consider
$\textsf{KDE}$ in the dynamic setting, and introduce a data structure that
efficiently maintains the estimates for a set of query points as data points
are added to $X$ over time. Based on this, we design a dynamic data structure
that maintains a sparse approximation of the fully connected similarity graph
on $X$, and develop a fast dynamic spectral clustering algorithm. We further
evaluate the effectiveness of our algorithms on both synthetic and real-world
datasets.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Steinar Laenen, Peter Macgregor, He Sun]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Faster Algorithm for Second (s,t)-mincut and Breaking Quadratic barrier for Dual Edge Sensitivity for (s,t)-mincut</title><link href="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-faster-algorithm-for-second-s-t-mincut-and-breaking-quadratic-barrier-for-dual-edge-sensitivity-for-s-t-mincut/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="arXiv: Data Structures and Algorithms: Faster Algorithm for Second (s,t)-mincut and Breaking Quadratic barrier for Dual Edge Sensitivity for (s,t)-mincut" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-faster-algorithm-for-second-s-t-mincut-and-breaking-quadratic-barrier-for-dual-edge-sensitivity-for-s-t-mincut</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://goravjindal.github.io/blog/2025/arxiv-data-structures-and-algorithms-faster-algorithm-for-second-s-t-mincut-and-breaking-quadratic-barrier-for-dual-edge-sensitivity-for-s-t-mincut/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Authors:</strong> <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Surender+Baswana">Surender Baswana</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Koustav+Bhanja">Koustav Bhanja</a>, <a href="https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=Anupam+Roy">Anupam Roy</a></p>

<p>We study (s,t)-cuts of second minimum capacity and present the following
algorithmic and graph-theoretic results.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Vazirani and Yannakakis [ICALP 1992] designed the first algorithm for
computing an (s,t)-cut of second minimum capacity using $O(n^2)$ maximum
(s,t)-flow computations. For directed integer-weighted graphs, we significantly
improve this bound by designing an algorithm that computes an $(s,t)$-cut of
second minimum capacity using $O(\sqrt{n})$ maximum (s,t)-flow computations
w.h.p. To achieve this result, a close relationship of independent interest is
established between $(s,t)$-cuts of second minimum capacity and global mincuts
in directed weighted graphs.</li>
  <li>Minimum+1 (s,t)-cuts have been studied quite well recently [Baswana,
Bhanja, and Pandey, ICALP 2022], which is a special case of second
(s,t)-mincut.
(a) For directed multi-graphs, we design an algorithm that, given any maximum
(s,t)-flow, computes a minimum+1 (s,t)-cut, if it exists, in $O(m)$ time.
(b) The existing structures for storing and characterizing all minimum+1
(s,t)-cuts occupy $O(mn)$ space. For undirected multi-graphs, we design a DAG
occupying only $O(m)$ space that stores and characterizes all minimum+1
(s,t)-cuts.</li>
  <li>The study of minimum+1 (s,t)-cuts often turns out to be useful in
designing dual edge sensitivity oracles – a compact data structure for
efficiently reporting an (s,t)-mincut after insertion/failure of any given pair
of query edges. It has been shown recently [Bhanja, ICALP 2025] that any dual
edge sensitivity oracle for (s,t)-mincut in undirected multi-graphs must occupy
${\Omega}(n^2)$ space in the worst-case, irrespective of the query time. For
simple graphs, we break this quadratic barrier while achieving a non-trivial
query time.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cstheoryrss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Authors: Surender Baswana, Koustav Bhanja, Anupam Roy]]></summary></entry></feed>